export const SOCIALSTUDIESA2018 = [

{
id: "question1",
question: "1. According to Abraham Maslow’s Hierarchy of Needs Theory, the basic need on man’s scale of preference is",
A: "achievement.",
B: "food.",
C: "friendship.",
D: "stability.",
answer: "B. food",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question2",
question: "2. One factor which hinders the development of the individual’s capabilities is",
A: "conducive home environment.",
B: "education and training.",
C: "guidance and counselling.",
D: "reliance on others for initiative.",
answer: "D. reliance on others for initiative",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question3",
question: "3. To accomplish a task successfully, the individual above all needs",
A: "self-esteem.",
B: "self-reliance.",
C: "intelligence.",
D: "determination,",
answer: "D. determination",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question4",
question: "4. The abuse of drugs is considered as",
A: "group interest.",
B: "social behaviour.",
C: "deviant behaviour.",
D: "personal misapplication.",
answer: "C. deviant behaviour",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question5",
question: "5. Responsible behaviour of adolescents often",
A: "leads to early marriages.",
B: "leads to teenage pregnancy.",
C: "encourages chastity before marriage.",
D: "results in human rights protection in society.",
answer: "C. encourage chastity before marriage",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question6",
question: "6. Which of the following options is the main objective associated with the celebration of festivals in Ghana?",
A: "An occasion to showcase what one has worked for",
B: "Home coming of members for development",
C: "Occasion to attract tourists",
D: "Opportunity to sell artefacts",
answer: "B. Home coming of members for development",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question7",
question: "7. Which of the following socio-cultural practices infringes on the rights of the individual and should therefore be abolished in the Ghanaian society?",
A: "Ancestral worship",
B: "Chieftaincy",
C: "Female circumcision",
D: "Traditional marriage",
answer: "C. Female circumcision",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question8",
question: "8. National symbols play the following significant roles except",
A: "fostering national integration.",
B: "portraying our taboos.",
C: "reflecting the wisdom of the people.",
D: "serving as a means of communication.",
answer: "B. portraying our taboo",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question9",
question: "9. In Ghanaian traditional society, the first stage of contracting marriage is",
A: "family.",
B: "ordinance.",
C: "religious.",
D: "traditional.",
answer: "D. traditional",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question10",
question: "10. Marriage is best sustained through",
A: "guidance and counselling.",
B: "love and understanding.",
C: "money and material wealth.",
D: "sexual satisfaction and beauty.",
answer: "B. love and understanding",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question11",
question: "11. The right to decide on the number of children in marriage is the responsibility of the",
A: "family.",
B: "couple.",
C: "husband.",
D: "wife.",
answer: "B. couple",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question12",
question: "12. The initial stage of customary marriage is",
A: "negotiation. ,",
B: "knocking.",
C: "mate selection.",
D: "payment of dowry.",
answer: "B. knocking",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question13",
question: "13. The family’s function of procreation primarily is to ensure",
A: "effective socialization and orientation.",
B: "proper parental care and maintenance.",
C: "transmission of family values.",
D: "continuity of the family and the lineage.",
answer: "D. continuity of the family and the lineage",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question14",
question: "14. In patrilineal system of inheritance, descent is traced along the line of the",
A: "mother.",
B: "father.",
C: "parents.",
D: "grandparents.",
answer: "B. father",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question15",
question: "15. Parenthood begins when the woman",
A: "is legally joined to the man.",
B: "undergoes puberty rites.",
C: "leaves the family home.",
D: "becomes pregnant.",
answer: "D. becomes pregnant",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question16",
question: "16. Which of the following options is an irresponsible behaviour of parents?",
A: "Finding fault with the children",
B: "Provision of physical needs of the children",
C: "Provision of moral training to the children",
D: "Socializing the children",
answer: "A. finding fault with the children",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question17",
question: "17. One factor that does not cause deviant behaviour among the youth is",
A: "frustration and deprivation.",
B: "hereditary traits.",
C: "lack of parental care.",
D: "peer pressure.",
answer: "B. hereditary traits",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question18",
question: "18. An agent of socialization is the",
A: "chief.",
B: "family.",
C: "media.",
D: "school.",
answer: "A. chief",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question19",
question: "19. Which of the following human activities helps in protecting the environment?",
A: "Adoption of appropriate fishing methods",
B: "Encouraging sand winning for building purposes",
C: "Increase in agricultural production",
D: "Intensive production of charcoal",
answer: "A. Adoption of appropriate fishing methods",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question20",
question: "20. To avoid flooding in our cities when it rains, there is the need for",
A: "responsible environmental officers.",
B: "modem architectural programmes.",
C: "well trained artisans.",
D: "well planned layouts.",
answer: "D. well planned layouts",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question21",
question: "21. Education is the total process of",
A: "acquiring book knowledge.",
B: "attending school.",
C: "being able to read and write.",
D: "human learning.",
answer: "D. human learning",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question22",
question: "22. To be self-reliant, Ghana must begin to",
A: "control her political and economic affairs.",
B: "build healthy and prosperous economy.",
C: "produce internal peace and security.",
D: "depend on her own efforts for development.",
answer: "D. depend on her own efforts for development",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question23",
question: "23. Which of the following conditions is closely linked with the independence of a country?",
A: "Globalization",
B: "Interdependence",
C: "Self-reliance",
D: "Self-realization",
answer: "C. Self-reliance",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question24",
question: "24. The best condition necessary for peace building in the Ghanaian society is",
A: "education and hard work.",
B: "justice and fairness.",
C: "religion and politics.",
D: "independence and productivity.",
answer: "B. justice and fairness",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question25",
question: "25. The following options are the characteristics of a good leader except",
A: "foresight.",
B: "intelligence.",
C: "obedience.",
D: "tolerance.",
answer: "B. intelligence",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question26",
question: "26. One major role a leader is expected to play in nation building is",
A: "having good health.",
B: "protecting the rights of deviants.",
C: "organizing his or her people for action.",
D: "possessing high intelligence.",
answer: "C. organizing his or her people for action",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question27",
question: "27. A constitution is important in nation building because it t",
A: "allows governments to exercise absolute power.",
B: "defends the country against external aggression.",
C: "makes the country self-reliant.",
D: "serves as a basis for good governance.",
answer: "D. serves as a basis for good governance",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question28",
question: "28. Socio-economic development is more sustainable under democratic system of governance because",
A: "of the existence of maintenance culture.",
B: "there is increased funding of projects.",
C: "minority and majority views are accommodated in decision making.",
D: "there is increased provision of incentive packages to workers.",
answer: "C. minority and majority views are accommodated in decision making",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question29",
question: "29. Which of the following responsibilities of a citizen is not highly obligatory?",
A: "Obedience to the law",
B: "Payment of taxes",
C: "Protection of state property",
D: "Standing for national election",
answer: "D. Standing for national election",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question30",
question: "30. One responsibility that is likely to conflict with an individual’s right to enjoy public social amenities is",
A: "defending the state.",
B: "going to school.",
C: "paying one’s taxes.",
D: "voting during elections.",
answer: "C. paying one's taxes",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question31",
question: "31. Ghana’s membership of the NEPAD initiative is to help",
A: "address her economic challenges.",
B: "institute a union government.",
C: "bring all heads of state institutions together.",
D: "bring all security agencies together.",
answer: "A. address her economic challenges",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question32",
question: "32. When many countries decide to work together to enhance development, they promote",
A: "bilateral co-operation.",
B: "economic co-operation.",
C: "technical co-operation.",
D: "multilateral co-operation.",
answer: "D. multilateral co-operation",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question33",
question: "33. A major benefit which the individual would derive from savings is to",
A: "buy luxurious cars.",
B: "ensure-educational development.",
C: "undertake infrastructural development.",
D: "undertake a leisure trip.",
answer: "B. ensure educational development",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question34",
question: "34. The most important amenity to be considered for a community dominated by the youth is",
A: "a court complex.",
B: "an entertainment spot.",
C: "a market square.",
D: "a school complex.",
answer: "D. trend of migration",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question35",
question: "35. Effective use of scientific knowledge is through",
A: "experimentation.",
B: "analysis.",
C: "research.",
D: "technology.",
answer: "D. technology",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question36",
question: "36. In which of the following ways does the world use science and technology for development? \nI. Development of communication gadgets \nII. Employment of skilled labour \nIII.	Introduction of agricultural machines \nIV.	Manufacture of drugs, food and chemicals",
A: "I and II",
B: "11 and IV",
C: "II, 111 and IV",
D: "I, III and IV",
answer: "D. I, III and V",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question37",
question: "37. Ghana’s resources are used mainly to promote",
A: "consumption of industrial products.",
B: "pollution of the environment.",
C: "social and economic development.",
D: "technological development.",
answer: "C. social and economic development",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question38",
question: "38. Which of the following decisions should be a priority for social development?",
A: "Maintaining squatters for votes’",
B: "Sacking squatters for personal benefits",
C: "Sacking squatters to construct school building",
D: "Sacking squatters to settle personal scores",
answer: "C. Sacking squatters to construct school building",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question39",
question: "39. A key feature of a buoyant economy is",
A: "effective political education.",
B: "high rate of industrialization.",
C: "high rate of population growth.",
D: "quality tertiary education.",
answer: "B. high rate of industrialization",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question40",
question: "40. Ghana’s effort to attain national economic development is hindered by",
A: "low dependency on primary products.",
B: "low population growth.",
C: "low rate of literacy.",
D: "positive attitude to work",
answer: "C. low rate of literacy",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question41",
question: "41. A major factor which affects sustainable development in Ghana is",
A: "frequent declaration of public holidays.",
B: "inadequate foreign assistance.",
C: "inadequate natural resources.",
D: "insufficient utilization of scientific knowledge.",
answer: "D. insufficient of scientific know ledge",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question42",
question: "42. One of the measures to adopt in sustaining growth and development in Ghana is",
A: "ensuring increase in population growth.",
B: "ensuring improvement in skills.",
C: "increasing access to portable water.",
D: "providing better incentives to people.",
answer: "B. ensuring improvement in skills",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question43",
question: "43. Moral degeneration among the youth in Ghana can be addressed by",
A: "placing emphasis on science education.",
B: "promoting religious tolerance among the youth.",
C: "providing guidance and counselling services.",
D: "spending more time with peers.",
answer: "C. providing guidance and counselling services",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question44",
question: "44. The phenomenon of under population occurs when the number of people in a country is",
A: "less than the available resources.",
B: "more than the available resources.",
C: "mostly made up of middle-aged people.",
D: "mostly made up of people below 18 years.",
answer: "A. less than the available resources",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question45",
question: "45. A factor that must promote people’s preference for an ideal family size is the",
A: "free distribution of contraceptives.",
B: "free distribution of school uniforms to pupils.",
C: "large compensation paid by government to small families.",
D: "quality rather than quantity of children.",
answer: "C. large compensational paid by government to small families",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question46",
question: "46. The youthful nature of Ghana’s population implies",
A: "affordable housing for the youth.",
B: "high dependency burden for the country.",
C: "low percentage of school going people.",
D: "widespread unhygienic environment.",
answer: "B. high dependency burden of the country",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question47",
question: "47. Punctuality, diligence and regularity are recipe to",
A: "fast productivity.",
B: "high productivity.",
C: "low productivity.",
D: "moderate productivity.",
answer: "B. high productivity",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question48",
question: "48. In a Joint Stock Company, risk is borne mainly by the",
A: "brokers.",
B: "employees.",
C: "employers.",
D: "shareholders.",
answer: "D. shareholders",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question49",
question: "49. For an individual to be gainfully employed in Ghana, he or she must initially",
A: "learn to write good curriculum vitae.",
B: "make personal contacts.",
C: "read newspapers for advertisements.",
D: "acquire the relevant education and skills.",
answer: "D. acquire the relevant education and skills",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question50",
question: "50. One effect of positive attitude to work in Ghana is the",
A: "attraction of foreign investment.",
B: "creation of more leisure time for workers.",
C: "extension of working hours.",
D: "increase in labour union activities.",
answer: "A. attraction of foreign investment",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},



]